<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<rss version="2.0">
 <channel>
  <title>William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Metrics Graphics'</title>
  <description>William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Metrics Graphics'</description>
  <link>https://wrla.ch/tags/Metrics-Graphics.html</link>
  <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 20:33:54 UT</lastBuildDate>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 20:33:54 UT</pubDate>
  <ttl>1800</ttl>
  <item>
   <title>Metrics Graphics: Stepping back for a while</title>
   <link>https://wrla.ch/blog/2019/09/metrics-graphics-stepping-back-for-a-while/?utm_source=Metrics-Graphics&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wrla-ch:-blog-2019-09-metrics-graphics-stepping-back-for-a-while</guid>
   <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 20:33:54 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Just a note that I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to step back from &lt;a href="https://metricsgraphicsjs.org"&gt;metrics graphics&lt;/a&gt; maintenance for the time being, which means that the project is essentially unowned. This has sort of been the case for a while, but I figured I should probably make it official.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you follow the link to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/metricsgraphics/metrics-graphics/"&gt;metrics graphics repository&lt;/a&gt;, you&amp;rsquo;ll note that the version has been bumped to &amp;ldquo;3.0-alpha3&amp;rdquo;. I was &lt;em&gt;this close&lt;/em&gt; to making one last new release this afternoon but decided I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to potentially break existing users who were fine using the last &amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo; version (v3.0 bumps the version of d3 used to &amp;ldquo;5&amp;rdquo;, among other breaking changes). I&amp;rsquo;d encourage people who want to continue using the library to make a fork and publish a copy under their user or organization name on npm.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>metricsgraphics movements</title>
   <link>https://wrla.ch/blog/2018/04/metricsgraphics-movements/?utm_source=Metrics-Graphics&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wrla-ch:-blog-2018-04-metricsgraphics-movements</guid>
   <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 15:20:32 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Just wanted to give a quick update on some things that have been happening with the &lt;a href="https://www.metricsgraphics.org"&gt;metrics graphics&lt;/a&gt; since I stepped up to help with maintainership a few months ago:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/hamilton"&gt;Hamilton&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s back as co-maintainer! This has been especially helpful  as he understands much of the historical context of metricsgraphics better than I do.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve merged in a large number of small fixes and improvements into the codebase,  thanks to myself and a number of other contributors. Special shout-out to Thomas  Champagne, who has contributed a &lt;a href="https://github.com/metricsgraphics/metrics-graphics/commits?author=thomaschampagne"&gt;large number of nifty new features&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;We moved the project from Mozilla to its &lt;a href="https://github.com/metricsgraphics/"&gt;own organization&lt;/a&gt; on  github. This feels like a much better way forward for a project which is supposed to be useful  far outside the bounds of Mozilla, and hopeful makes contributors feel more like the first-class  citizens of the project that they actually are.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;We have a GSOC intern! As part of the Mozilla GSOC, Yunhao Zheng is going to be working on  adding rich brushing/zooming support to Metrics Graphics, which should be quite useful for  visualizing complex data in projects like &lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/EngineeringProductivity/Projects/Perfherder"&gt;Perfherder&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1_KIOJtemqlCBktDdfdjDuS4XhICeaKO3QhNRwbnnf-g/"&gt;Project outline&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/projects/#5422620527296512"&gt;Yunhao&amp;rsquo;s proposal&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>