<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<rss version="2.0">
 <channel>
  <title>William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Mozilla'</title>
  <description>William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Mozilla'</description>
  <link>https://wlach.github.io/tags/Mozilla.html</link>
  <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2020 16:08:57 UT</lastBuildDate>
  <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2020 16:08:57 UT</pubDate>
  <ttl>1800</ttl>
  <item>
   <title>Conda is pretty great</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2020/01/conda-is-pretty-great/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2020-01-conda-is-pretty-great</guid>
   <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2020 16:08:57 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Lately the data engineering team has been looking into productionizing (i.e. running in Airflow) a bunch of models that the data science team has been producing. This often involves languages and environments that are a bit outside of our comfort zone &amp;mdash; for example, &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/missioncontrol-v2"&gt;the next version of Mission Control&lt;/a&gt; relies on the &lt;a href="https://mc-stan.org/users/interfaces/rstan"&gt;R-stan library&lt;/a&gt; to produce a model of expected crash behaviour as Firefox is released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make things as simple and deterministic as possible, we&amp;rsquo;ve been building up Docker containers to run/execute this code along with their dependencies, which makes things nice and reproducible. My initial thought was to use just the language-native toolchains to build up my container for the above project, but quickly found a number of problems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;For local testing, Docker on Mac is &lt;em&gt;slow&lt;/em&gt;: when doing a large number of statistical calculations (as above), you can count on your testing iterations taking 3 to 4 (or more) times longer.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;On initial setup, the default R packaging strategy is to have the user of a package like R-stan recompile from source. This can take &lt;em&gt;forever&lt;/em&gt; if you have a long list of dependencies with C-compiled extensions (pretty much a given if you&amp;rsquo;re working in the data space): rebuilding my initial docker environment for missioncontrol-v2 took almost an hour. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just a problem for local development: it also makes continuous integration using a service like Circle or Travis expensive and painful.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been vaguely aware of &lt;a href="https://docs.conda.io/en/latest/"&gt;Conda&lt;/a&gt; for a few years, but didn&amp;rsquo;t really understand its value proposition until I started working on the above project: why bother with a heavyweight package manager when you already have Docker to virtualize things? The answer is that it solves both of the above problems: for local development, you can get something more-or-less identical to what you&amp;rsquo;re running inside Docker with no performance penalty whatsoever. And for building the docker container itself, Conda&amp;rsquo;s package repository contains pre-compiled versions of all the dependencies you&amp;rsquo;d want to use for something like this (even somewhat esoteric libraries like R-stan are available on &lt;a href="https://conda-forge.org/"&gt;conda-forge&lt;/a&gt;), which brought my build cycle times down to less than 5 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;tl;dr: If you have a bunch of R / python code you want to run in a reproducible manner, consider Conda.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Using BigQuery JavaScript UDFs to analyze Firefox telemetry for fun &amp; profit</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2019/10/using-bigquery-javascript-udfs-to-analyze-firefox-telemetry-for-fun-profit/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2019-10-using-bigquery-javascript-udfs-to-analyze-firefox-telemetry-for-fun-profit</guid>
   <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2019 15:11:17 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;For the last year, we&amp;rsquo;ve been gradually migrating our backend Telemetry systems from AWS to GCP. I&amp;rsquo;ve been helping out here and there with this effort, most recently porting a job we used to detect slow tab spinners in Firefox nightly, which produced a small dataset that feeds a &lt;a href="https://mikeconley.github.io/bug1310250/"&gt;small adhoc dashboard&lt;/a&gt; which Mike Conley maintains. This was a relatively small task as things go, but it highlighted some features and improvements which I think might be broadly interesting, so I decided to write up a small blog post about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially all this dashboard tells you is what percentage of the Firefox nightly population saw a tab spinner over the past 6 months. And of those that did see a tab spinner, what was the severity? Essentially we’re just trying to make sure that there are no major regressions of user experience (and also that efforts to improve things bore fruit):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img style="width:600px" srcset="/files/2019/10/tab-spinner-dash.png" /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty simple stuff, but getting the data necessary to produce this kind of dashboard used to be anything but trivial: while some common business/product questions could be answered by a quick query to &lt;a href="https://docs.telemetry.mozilla.org/datasets/batch_view/clients_daily/reference.html"&gt;clients_daily&lt;/a&gt;, getting engineering-specific metrics like this usually involved trawling through gigabytes of raw heka encoded blobs using an Apache Spark cluster and then extracting the relevant information out of the telemetry probe histograms (in this case, &lt;code&gt;FX_TAB_SWITCH_SPINNER_VISIBLE_MS&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;FX_TAB_SWITCH_SPINNER_VISIBLE_LONG_MS&lt;/code&gt;) contained therein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code itself was rather complicated (&lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/python_mozetl/blob/58dce245ce8012b338e8b102a8c2c0f00601be60/mozetl/tab_spinner/tab_spinner.py"&gt;take a look, if you dare&lt;/a&gt;) but even worse, running it could get &lt;em&gt;very expensive&lt;/em&gt;. We had a 14 node cluster churning through this script daily, and it took on average about an hour and a half to run! I don&amp;rsquo;t have the exact cost figures on hand (and am not sure if I&amp;rsquo;d be authorized to share them if I did), but based on a back of the envelope sketch, this one single script was probably costing us somewhere on the order of $10-$40 a day (that works out to between $3650-$14600 a year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With our move to &lt;a href="https://cloud.google.com/bigquery/"&gt;BigQuery&lt;/a&gt;, things get a lot simpler! Thanks to the combined effort of my team and data operations[1], we now produce &amp;ldquo;stable&amp;rdquo; ping tables on a daily basis with &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the relevant histogram data (stored as JSON blobs), queryable using relatively vanilla SQL. In this case, the data we care about is in &lt;code&gt;telemetry.main&lt;/code&gt; (named after the main ping, appropriately enough). With the help of a small &lt;a href="https://cloud.google.com/bigquery/docs/reference/standard-sql/user-defined-functions"&gt;JavaScript UDF&lt;/a&gt; function, all of this data can easily be extracted into a table inside a single SQL query scheduled by &lt;a href="https://docs.telemetry.mozilla.org/tools/stmo.html"&gt;sql.telemetry.mozilla.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;CREATE TEMP FUNCTION
  udf_js_json_extract_highest_long_spinner (input STRING)
  RETURNS INT64
  LANGUAGE js AS """
    if (input == null) {
      return 0;
    }
    var result = JSON.parse(input);
    var valuesMap = result.values;
    var highest = 0;
    for (var key in valuesMap) {
      var range = parseInt(key);
      if (valuesMap[key]) {
        highest = range &amp;gt; 0 ? range : 1;
      }
    }
    return highest;
""";

SELECT build_id,
sum (case when highest &amp;gt;= 64000 then 1 else 0 end) as v_64000ms_or_higher,
sum (case when highest &amp;gt;= 27856 and highest &amp;lt; 64000 then 1 else 0 end) as v_27856ms_to_63999ms,
sum (case when highest &amp;gt;= 12124 and highest &amp;lt; 27856 then 1 else 0 end) as v_12124ms_to_27855ms,
sum (case when highest &amp;gt;= 5277 and highest &amp;lt; 12124 then 1 else 0 end) as v_5277ms_to_12123ms,
sum (case when highest &amp;gt;= 2297 and highest &amp;lt; 5277 then 1 else 0 end) as v_2297ms_to_5276ms,
sum (case when highest &amp;gt;= 1000 and highest &amp;lt; 2297 then 1 else 0 end) as v_1000ms_to_2296ms,
sum (case when highest &amp;gt; 0 and highest &amp;lt; 50 then 1 else 0 end) as v_0ms_to_49ms,
sum (case when highest &amp;gt;= 50 and highest &amp;lt; 100 then 1 else 0 end) as v_50ms_to_99ms,
sum (case when highest &amp;gt;= 100 and highest &amp;lt; 200 then 1 else 0 end) as v_100ms_to_199ms,
sum (case when highest &amp;gt;= 200 and highest &amp;lt; 400 then 1 else 0 end) as v_200ms_to_399ms,
sum (case when highest &amp;gt;= 400 and highest &amp;lt; 800 then 1 else 0 end) as v_400ms_to_799ms,
count(*) as count
from
(select build_id, client_id, max(greatest(highest_long, highest_short)) as highest
from
(SELECT
    SUBSTR(application.build_id, 0, 8) as build_id,
    client_id,
    udf_js_json_extract_highest_long_spinner(payload.histograms.FX_TAB_SWITCH_SPINNER_VISIBLE_LONG_MS) AS highest_long,
    udf_js_json_extract_highest_long_spinner(payload.histograms.FX_TAB_SWITCH_SPINNER_VISIBLE_MS) as highest_short
FROM telemetry.main
WHERE
    application.channel='nightly'
    AND normalized_os='Windows'
    AND application.build_id &amp;gt; FORMAT_DATE("%Y%m%d", DATE_SUB(CURRENT_DATE(), INTERVAL 2 QUARTER))
    AND DATE(submission_timestamp) &amp;gt;= DATE_SUB(CURRENT_DATE(), INTERVAL 2 QUARTER))
group by build_id, client_id) group by build_id;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to being much simpler, this new job is also &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; cheaper. The last run of it scanned just over 1 TB of data, meaning it cost us just over $5. Not as cheap as I might like, but considerably less expensive than before: I&amp;rsquo;ve also scheduled it to only run once every other day, since Mike tells me he doesn&amp;rsquo;t need this data any more often than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] I understand that Jeff Klukas, Frank Bertsch, Daniel Thorn, Anthony Miyaguchi, and Wesley Dawson are the principals involved - apologies if I&amp;rsquo;m forgetting someone.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Metrics Graphics: Stepping back for a while</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2019/09/metrics-graphics-stepping-back-for-a-while/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2019-09-metrics-graphics-stepping-back-for-a-while</guid>
   <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 20:33:54 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Just a note that I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to step back from &lt;a href="https://metricsgraphicsjs.org"&gt;metrics graphics&lt;/a&gt; maintenance for the time being, which means that the project is essentially unowned. This has sort of been the case for a while, but I figured I should probably make it official.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you follow the link to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/metricsgraphics/metrics-graphics/"&gt;metrics graphics repository&lt;/a&gt;, you&amp;rsquo;ll note that the version has been bumped to &amp;ldquo;3.0-alpha3&amp;rdquo;. I was &lt;em&gt;this close&lt;/em&gt; to making one last new release this afternoon but decided I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to potentially break existing users who were fine using the last &amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo; version (v3.0 bumps the version of d3 used to &amp;ldquo;5&amp;rdquo;, among other breaking changes). I&amp;rsquo;d encourage people who want to continue using the library to make a fork and publish a copy under their user or organization name on npm.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>mozregression update: python 3 edition</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2019/09/mozregression-update-python-3-edition/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2019-09-mozregression-update-python-3-edition</guid>
   <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2019 15:29:04 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;For those who are still wondering, yup, I am still maintaining &lt;a href="https://mozilla.github.io/mozregression/"&gt;mozregression&lt;/a&gt;, though increasingly reluctantly. Given how important this project is to the development of Firefox (getting a regression window using mozregression is standard operating procedure whenever a new bug is reported in Firefox), it feels like this project is pretty vital, so I continue out of some sense of obligation &amp;mdash; but really, someone more interested in Mozilla&amp;rsquo;a build, automation and testing systems would be better suited to this task: over the past few years, my interests/focus have shifted away from this area to building up Mozilla&amp;rsquo;s data storage and visualization platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will describe some of the things that have happened in the last year and where I see the project going. My hope is to attract some new blood to add some needed features to the project and maybe take on some of the maintainership duties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="python-3"&gt;python 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important update is that, as of today, the command-line version of mozregression (v3.0.1) should work with python 3.5+. &lt;a href="https://python-modernize.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;modernize&lt;/a&gt; did most of the work for us, though there were some unit tests that needed updating: special thanks to &lt;a href="https://github.com/gloomy-ghost"&gt;@gloomy-ghost&lt;/a&gt; for helping with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, we will continue to support python 2.7 in parallel, mainly because the GUI has not yet been ported to python 3 (more on that later) and we have CI to make sure it doesn&amp;rsquo;t break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-updates"&gt;other updates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last year has mostly been one of maintenance. Thanks in particular to Ian Moody (:kwan) for his work throughout the year &amp;mdash; including patches to adapt mozregression support to our new updates policy and shippable builds (&lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1532412"&gt;bug 1532412&lt;/a&gt;), and Kartikaya Gupta (:kats) for adding support for bisecting the GeckoView example app (&lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1507225"&gt;bug 1507225&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="future-work"&gt;future work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a bunch of things I see us wanting to add or change with mozregression over the next year or so. I might get to some of these if I have some spare cycles, but probably best not to count on it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Port the mozregression GUI to Python 3 (&lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1581633"&gt;bug  1581633&lt;/a&gt;) As mentioned  above, the command-line client works with python 3, but we have yet to port  the &lt;a href=""&gt;GUI&lt;/a&gt;. We should do that. This probably also entails porting the GUI to  use PyQT5 (which is pip-installable and thus much easier to integrate into a  CI process), see &lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1426766"&gt;bug 1426766&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Make self-contained GUI builds available for MacOS X (&lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1425105"&gt;bug  1425105&lt;/a&gt;) and Linux  (&lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1581643"&gt;bug 1581643&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Improve our mechanism for producing a standalone version of the GUI in  general. We&amp;rsquo;ve used &lt;a href="https://github.com/anthony-tuininga/cx_Freeze"&gt;cx_Freeze&lt;/a&gt;  which mostly works ok, but has a number of problems (e.g. it pulls in a bunch of unnecessary dependencies, which  bloats the size of the installer). Upgrading the GUI to use python 3 may  alleviate some of these issues, but it might be worth considering other  options in this space, like Gregory Szorc&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://github.com/indygreg/PyOxidizer"&gt;pyoxidizer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Add some kind of telemetry to mozregression to measure usage of this tool  (&lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1581647"&gt;bug 1581647&lt;/a&gt;).  My anecdotal experience is that this tool is pretty invaluable for Firefox  development and QA, but this is not immediately apparent to Mozilla&amp;rsquo;s  leadership and it&amp;rsquo;s thus very difficult to convince people to spend their  cycles on maintaining and improving this tool. Field data may help change  that story.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Supporting new Mozilla products which aren&amp;rsquo;t built (entirely) out of mozilla-central,  most especially Fenix (&lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1556042"&gt;bug 1556042&lt;/a&gt;)  and Firefox Reality (&lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1568488"&gt;bug 1568488&lt;/a&gt;).  This is probably rather involved (mozregression has a big pile of assumptions about how  the builds it pulls down are stored and organized) but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that  this work isn&amp;rsquo;t necessary.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in working on any of the above, please feel free to dive in on one of the above bugs. I can&amp;rsquo;t offer formal mentorship, but am happy to help out where I can.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Time for some project updates</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2019/09/time-for-some-project-updates/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2019-09-time-for-some-project-updates</guid>
   <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2019 14:41:39 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been a bit bad about updating this blog over the past year or so, though this hasn&amp;rsquo;t meant there haven&amp;rsquo;t been things to talk about. For the next couple weeks, I&amp;rsquo;m going to try to give some updates on the projects I have been spending time on in the past year, both old and new. I&amp;rsquo;m going to begin with some of the less-loved things I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on, partially in an attempt to motivate some forward-motion on things that I believe are rather important to Mozilla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More to come.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>New ideas, old buildings</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2019/03/new-ideas-old-buildings/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2019-03-new-ideas-old-buildings</guid>
   <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 19:08:11 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Last week, Brendan Colloran &lt;a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2019/03/iodide-an-experimental-tool-for-scientific-communicatiodide-for-scientific-communication-exploration-on-the-web/"&gt;announced Iodide&lt;/a&gt;, a new take on scientific collaboration and reporting that I&amp;rsquo;ve been really happy to contribute to over the past year-and-a-bit. I&amp;rsquo;ve been describing it to people I meet as kind of "&lt;a href="https://glitch.com/"&gt;glitch&lt;/a&gt; meets &lt;a href="https://jupyter.org/"&gt;jupyter&lt;/a&gt; " but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t quite do it justice. I&amp;rsquo;d recommend reading Brendan&amp;rsquo;s blog post (and taking a look at our &lt;a href="https://alpha.iodide.io"&gt;demonstration site&lt;/a&gt;) to get the full picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One question that I&amp;rsquo;ve heard asked (including on Brendan&amp;rsquo;s post) is why we chose a rather conventional and old technology (&lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt;) for the server backend. Certainly, Iodide has not been shy about building with relatively new or experimental technologies for other parts (e.g. Python on WebAssembly for the notebooks, React/Redux for the frontend). Why not complete the cycle by using a new-fangled JavaScript web server like, I don&amp;rsquo;t know, &lt;a href="https://nestjs.com/"&gt;NestJS&lt;/a&gt;? And while we&amp;rsquo;re at it, what&amp;rsquo;s with iodide&amp;rsquo;s ridiculous &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_state_transfer"&gt;REST API&lt;/a&gt;? Don&amp;rsquo;t you know &lt;a href="https://graphql.org/"&gt;GraphQL&lt;/a&gt; is the only legitimate way to expose your backend to the world in 2019?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great urban theorist of the twentieth century, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jane_Jacobs"&gt;Jane Jacobs&lt;/a&gt; has a quote I love:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
 &lt;i&gt;“Old ideas can sometimes use new buildings. New ideas must use old buildings.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laura Thompson (an engineering director at Mozilla) has restated this wisdom in a software development context as &lt;a href="https://speakerdeck.com/lauraxt/build-exciting-things-with-boring-technologies"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Build exciting things with boring technologies&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It so happened that the server was not an area Iodide was focusing on for innovation (at least initially), so it made much, much more sense to use something proven and battle-tested for the server side deployment. I&amp;rsquo;d used Django for a number of projects at Mozilla before this one (&lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/treeherder"&gt;Treeherder/Perfherder&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/missioncontrol/"&gt;Mission Control&lt;/a&gt;) and have been wildly impressed by the project&amp;rsquo;s excellent &lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/"&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/2.1/topics/db/"&gt;database access layer&lt;/a&gt;, and support for building a standardized API via the &lt;a href="https://www.django-rest-framework.org/"&gt;Django REST Framework&lt;/a&gt; add-on. Not to mention the fact that so much of Mozilla&amp;rsquo;s in-house ops and web development expertise is based around this framework (I could name off probably 5 or 6 internal business systems based around the Django stack, in addition to Treeherder), so deploying Iodide and getting help building it would be something of a known quantity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only slightly more than half a year since I began work on the iodide server, we now have both a publicly accessible site for others to experiment with &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; an internal one for Mozilla&amp;rsquo;s business needs. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to say what would have happened had I chosen something more experimental to build Iodide&amp;rsquo;s server piece, but at the very least there would have been a substantial learning curve involved &amp;mdash; in addition to engineering effort to fill in the gaps where the new technology is not yet complete &amp;mdash; which would have meant less time to innovate where it really mattered. Django&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/2.1/topics/migrations/"&gt;database migration system&lt;/a&gt;, for example, took years to come to fruition and I&amp;rsquo;m not aware of anything comparable in the world of JavaScript web frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move ahead, we may find places where applying new backend server technologies makes sense. Heck, maybe we&amp;rsquo;ll chose to rewrite the whole thing at some point. But to get to launch, chosing a bunch of boring, tested software for this portion of Iodide was (in my view) absolutely the right decision and I make no apologies for it.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Making contribution work for Firefox tooling and data projects</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2018/11/making-contribution-work-for-firefox-tooling-and-data-projects/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2018-11-making-contribution-work-for-firefox-tooling-and-data-projects</guid>
   <pubDate>Mon, 26 Nov 2018 16:13:46 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite parts about Mozilla is mentoring and working alongside third party contributors. Somewhat surprisingly since I work on internal tools, I&amp;rsquo;ve had a fair amount of luck finding people to help work on projects within my purview: &lt;a href="https://mozilla.github.io/mozregression"&gt;mozregression&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/EngineeringProductivity/Projects/Perfherder"&gt;perfherder&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://metricsgraphics.org"&gt;metrics graphics&lt;/a&gt;, and others have all benefited from the contributions of people outside of Mozilla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases (a notable exception being metrics graphics), these have been internal-tooling projects used by others to debug, develop, or otherwise understand the behaviour of Firefox. On the face of it, none of the things I work on are exactly &amp;ldquo;high profile cutting edge stuff&amp;rdquo; in the way, say, Firefox or the Rust Programming Language are. So why do they bother? The exact formula varies depending on contributor, but I think it usually comes down to some combination of these two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;A desire to learn and demonstrate competence with industry standard  tooling (the python programming language, frontend web development, backend  databases, &amp;ldquo;big data&amp;rdquo; technologies like Parquet, &amp;hellip;).&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;A desire to work with and gain recognition inside of a community of  like-minded people.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty basic, obvious stuff &amp;mdash; there is an appeal here to basic human desires like the need for security and a sense of belonging. Once someone&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;in the loop&amp;rdquo;, so to speak, generally things take care of themselves. The real challenge, I&amp;rsquo;ve found, is getting people from the &amp;ldquo;I am potentially interested in doing something with Mozilla internal tools&amp;rdquo; to the stage that they are confident and competent enough to work in a reasonably self-directed way. When I was on the A-Team, we classified this transition in terms of a &lt;a href="https://ateam-bootcamp.readthedocs.io/en/latest/guide/curve.html"&gt;commitment curve&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img srcset="/files/2018/11/commitment-curve-visualization.png 2x" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1080119"&gt;prototype commitment curve graphic by Steven Brown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hardest part, in my experience, is the initial part of that curve. At this point, people are just dipping their toe in the water. Some may not have a ton of experience with software development yet. In other cases, my projects may just not be the right fit for them. But of course, sometimes there is a fit, or at least one could be developed! What I&amp;rsquo;ve found most helpful is &amp;ldquo;clearing a viable path&amp;rdquo; forward for the right kind of contributor. That is, some kind of initial hypothesis of what a successful contribution experience would look like as a new person transitions from &amp;ldquo;explorer&amp;rdquo; stage in the chart above to &amp;ldquo;associate&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly have a perfect template for what &amp;ldquo;clearing a path&amp;rdquo; looks like in every case. It depends quite a bit on the nature of the contributor. But there are some common themes that I&amp;rsquo;ve found effective:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, provide good, concise documentation both on the project&amp;rsquo;s purpose and vision and how to get started easily and keep it up to date. For projects with a front-end web component, I try to decouple the front end parts from the backend services so that people can &lt;code&gt;yarn install &amp;amp;&amp;amp; yarn start&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href="/blog/2014/09/hacking-on-the-treeherder-front-end-refreshingly-easy/"&gt;their way to success&lt;/a&gt;. Being able to &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; the project in action quickly (and not getting stuck on some mundane getting started step) is key in maintaining initial interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, provide a set of good starter issues (sometimes called &amp;ldquo;good first bugs&amp;rdquo;) for people to work on. Generally these would be non-critical-path type issues that have straightforward instructions to resolve and fix. Again, the idea here is to give people a sense of quick progress and resolution, a &amp;ldquo;yes I can actually do this&amp;rdquo; sort of feeling. But be careful not to let a contributor get stuck here! These bugs take a disproportionate amount of effort to file and mentor compared to their actual value &amp;mdash; the key is to progress the contributor to the next level once it&amp;rsquo;s clear they can handle the basics involved in solving such an issue (checking out the source code, applying a fix, submitting a patch, etc). Otherwise you&amp;rsquo;re going to feel frustrated and wonder why you&amp;rsquo;re on an endless treadmill of writing up trivial bugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, once a contributor has established themselves by fixing a few of these simple issues, I try to get to know them a little better. Send them an email, learn where they&amp;rsquo;re from, invite them to chat on the project channel if they can. At the same time, this is an opportunity to craft a somewhat larger piece of work (a sort of mini-project) that they can do, tailored to the interests. For example, a new contributor on the Mission Control has recently been working on adding &lt;a href="https://jestjs.io/"&gt;Jest&lt;/a&gt; tests to the project &amp;mdash; I provided some basic guidance of things to look at, but did not dictate exactly &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to perform the task. They figured that out for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As time goes by, you just continue this process. Depending on the contributor, they may start coming up with their own ideas for how a project might be improved or they might still want to follow your lead (or that of the team), but at the least I generally see an improvement in their self-directedness and confidence after a period of sustained contribution. In either case, the key to success remains the same: sustained and positive communication and sharing of goals and aspirations, making sure that both parties are getting something positive out of the experience. Where possible, I try to include contributors in team meetings. Where there&amp;rsquo;s an especially close working relationship (e.g. &lt;a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/archive/"&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt;). I try to set up a weekly one on one. Regardless, I make reviewing code, answering questions, and providing suggestions on how to move forward a top priority (i.e. not something I&amp;rsquo;ll leave for a few days). It&amp;rsquo;s the least I can do if someone is willing to take time out to contribute to my project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this seems similar to the best practices for how members of a team should onboard each other and work together, that&amp;rsquo;s not really a coincidence. Obviously the relationship is a little different because we&amp;rsquo;re not operating with a formal managerial structure and usually the work is unpaid: I try to bear that mind and make double sure that contributors are really getting some useful skills and habits that they can take with them to future jobs and other opportunities, while also emphasizing that their code contributions are their own, not Mozilla&amp;rsquo;s. So far it seems to have worked out pretty well for all concerned (me, Mozilla, and the contributors).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Mission Control 1.0</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2018/06/mission-control-1-0/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2018-06-mission-control-1-0</guid>
   <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 21:50:32 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Just a quick announcement that the first &amp;ldquo;production-ready&amp;rdquo; version of Mission Control just went live yesterday, at this easy-to-remember URL:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://missioncontrol.telemetry.mozilla.org"&gt;https://missioncontrol.telemetry.mozilla.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those not yet familiar with the project, Mission Control aims to track release stability and quality across Firefox releases. It is similar in spirit to arewestableyet and other crash dashboards, with the following new and exciting properties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Uses the full set of crash counts gathered via telemetry, rather than the arbitrary  sample that users decide to submit to crash-stats&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Results are available within minutes of ingestion by telemetry (although be warned  &lt;a href="/blog/2017/10/better-or-worse-by-what-measure/"&gt;initial results for a release always look bad&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;The denominator in our crash rate is usage hours, rather than the probably-incorrect  calculation of active-daily-installs used by  &lt;a href="https://arewestableyet.com"&gt;arewestableyet&lt;/a&gt; (not a knock on the people who  wrote that tool, there was nothing better available at the time)&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;We have a detailed breakdown of the results by platform (rather than letting Windows  results dominate the overall rates due to its high volume of usage)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, my hope is that this tool will provide a more scientific and accurate idea of release stability and quality over time. There&amp;rsquo;s lots more to do, but I think this is a promising start. Much gratitude to &lt;a href="https://home.kairo.at/blog/2014-04/how_effective_is_the_stability_program"&gt;kairo&lt;/a&gt;, calixte, &lt;a href="https://chuttenblog.wordpress.com/"&gt;chutten&lt;/a&gt; and others who helped build my understanding of this area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dashboard itself an easier thing to show than talk about, so I recorded a quick demonstration of some of the dashboard&amp;rsquo;s capabilities and published it on air mozilla:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src="https://air.mozilla.org/mission-control-dashboard-intro/video/" width="896" height="524" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://air.mozilla.org/mission-control-dashboard-intro/"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>metricsgraphics movements</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2018/04/metricsgraphics-movements/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2018-04-metricsgraphics-movements</guid>
   <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 15:20:32 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Just wanted to give a quick update on some things that have been happening with the &lt;a href="https://www.metricsgraphics.org"&gt;metrics graphics&lt;/a&gt; since I stepped up to help with maintainership a few months ago:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/hamilton"&gt;Hamilton&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s back as co-maintainer! This has been especially helpful  as he understands much of the historical context of metricsgraphics better than I do.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve merged in a large number of small fixes and improvements into the codebase,  thanks to myself and a number of other contributors. Special shout-out to Thomas  Champagne, who has contributed a &lt;a href="https://github.com/metricsgraphics/metrics-graphics/commits?author=thomaschampagne"&gt;large number of nifty new features&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;We moved the project from Mozilla to its &lt;a href="https://github.com/metricsgraphics/"&gt;own organization&lt;/a&gt; on  github. This feels like a much better way forward for a project which is supposed to be useful  far outside the bounds of Mozilla, and hopeful makes contributors feel more like the first-class  citizens of the project that they actually are.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;We have a GSOC intern! As part of the Mozilla GSOC, Yunhao Zheng is going to be working on  adding rich brushing/zooming support to Metrics Graphics, which should be quite useful for  visualizing complex data in projects like &lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/EngineeringProductivity/Projects/Perfherder"&gt;Perfherder&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1_KIOJtemqlCBktDdfdjDuS4XhICeaKO3QhNRwbnnf-g/"&gt;Project outline&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/projects/#5422620527296512"&gt;Yunhao&amp;rsquo;s proposal&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Mission Control update</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2018/04/mission-control-update/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2018-04-mission-control-update</guid>
   <pubDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2018 18:46:43 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Yep, still working on this project. We&amp;rsquo;ve shifted gears somewhat from trying to identify problems in a time series of error aggregates to tracking somewhat longer term trends release over release, to fill the needs of the release management team at Mozilla. It&amp;rsquo;s been a good change, I think. A bit of a tighter focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main motivator for this work is that the ADI (active daily install) numbers that crash stats used to provide as input to a similar service, &lt;a href="https://arewestableyet.com"&gt;AreWeStableYet&lt;/a&gt; (link requires Mozilla credentials), are going away and we need some kind of replacement. I&amp;rsquo;ve been learning about this older system worked (this &lt;a href="https://home.kairo.at/blog/2014-04/how_effective_is_the_stability_program"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; from KaiRo was helpful) and trying to develop a replacement which reproduces some of its useful characteristics while also taking advantage of some of the new features that are provided by the &lt;a href="https://docs.telemetry.mozilla.org/datasets/streaming/error_aggregates/reference.html"&gt;error_aggregates&lt;/a&gt; dataset and the mission control user interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some preliminary screenshots of what I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to come up with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img style="width:400px" srcset="/files/2018/04/missioncontrol-main-view.png 2x" /&gt; &lt;img style="width:400px" srcset="/files/2018/04/missioncontrol-windows-release.png 2x" /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key things to keep in mind with this dashboard is that by default it shows an &lt;em&gt;adjusted&lt;/em&gt; set of rates (defined as total number of events divided by total usage khours), which means we compare the latest release to the previous one within the same time interval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if, say, the latest release is &amp;ldquo;59&amp;rdquo; and it&amp;rsquo;s been out for two weeks, we will compare it against the previous release (&amp;ldquo;58&amp;rdquo;) in its first two weeks. As I&amp;rsquo;ve said here before, things are &lt;a href="/blog/2017/10/better-or-worse-by-what-measure"&gt;always crashier when they first go out&lt;/a&gt;, and comparing a new release to one that has been out in the field for some time is not a fair comparison at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adjusted view of things is still not apples-to-apples: the causality of crashes and errors is so complex that there will always be differences between releases which are beyond our control or even understanding. Many crash reports, for example, have nothing to do with our product but with third party software and web sites beyond our control. That said, I feel like this adjusted rate is still good enough to tell us (broadly speaking) (1) whether our latest release / beta / nightly is ok (i.e. there is no major showstopper issue) and (2) whether our overall error rate is going up or down over several versions (if there is a continual increase in our crash rate, it might point to a problem in our release/qa process).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the first things that we&amp;rsquo;ve found with this system are not real problems with the product but data collection issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1447161"&gt;we don&amp;rsquo;t seem to be collecting counts of gmplugin crashes on Windows anymore via telemetry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1413172#c8"&gt;the number of content_shutdown_crashes is greater than the number of content_crashes, even though the former is a superset of the latter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data issues aside, the indications are that there&amp;rsquo;s been a steady increase in the quality of Firefox over the last few releases based on the main user facing error metric we&amp;rsquo;ve cared about in the past (main crashes), so that&amp;rsquo;s good. :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to play with the system yourself, the &lt;a href="https://data-missioncontrol.dev.mozaws.net/"&gt;development instance&lt;/a&gt; is still up. We will probably look at making this thing &amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo; next quarter.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Derived versus direct</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2018/02/derived-versus-direct/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2018-02-derived-versus-direct</guid>
   <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2018 21:06:40 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;To attempt to make complex phenomena more understandable, we often use derived measures when representing Telemetry data at Mozilla. For error rates for example, we often measure things in terms of &amp;ldquo;X per khours of use&amp;rdquo; (where X might be &amp;ldquo;main crashes&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;appearance of the slow script dialogue&amp;rdquo;). I.e. instead of showing a raw &lt;em&gt;count&lt;/em&gt; of errors we show a rate. Normally this is a good thing: it allows the user to easily compare two things which might have different raw numbers for whatever reason but where you&amp;rsquo;d normally expect the ratio to be similar. For example, we see that although the &lt;em&gt;uptake&lt;/em&gt; of the newly-released Firefox 58.0.2 is a bit slower than 58.0.1, the overall crash rate (as sampled every 5 minutes) is more or less the same after about a day has rolled around:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img srcset="/files/2018/02/main_crashes_normalized.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, looking at raw counts doesn&amp;rsquo;t really give you much of a hint on how to interpret the results. Depending on the scale of the graph, the actual rates could actually resolve to being vastly different:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img srcset="/files/2018/02/main_crashes_raw.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so this simple tool (using a ratio) is useful. Yay! Unfortunately, there is one case where using this technique can lead to a very deceptive visualization: when the number of samples is really small, a few outliers can give a really false impression of what&amp;rsquo;s really happening. Take this graph of what the crash rate looked like &lt;em&gt;just after&lt;/em&gt; Firefox 58.0 was released:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img srcset="/files/2018/02/relative_small_crash_counts.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10 to 100 errors per 1000 hours, say it isn&amp;rsquo;t so? But wait, how many errors do we have absolutely? Hovering over a representative point in the graph with the normalization (use of a ratio) turned off:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img srcset="/files/2018/02/absolute_small_crash_counts.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re really only talking about something between 1 to 40 crashes events over a relatively small number of usage hours. This is clearly so little data that we can&amp;rsquo;t (and shouldn&amp;rsquo;t) draw any kind of conclusion whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so that&amp;rsquo;s just science 101: don&amp;rsquo;t jump to conclusions based on small, vastly unrepresentative samples. Unfortunately due to human psychology people tend to assume that charts like this are authoritative and represent something real, absent an explanation otherwise &amp;mdash; and the use of a ratio obscured the one fact (extreme lack of data) that would have given the user a hint on how to correctly interpret the results. Something to keep in mind as we build our tools.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Giving and receiving help at Mozilla</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2018/01/giving-and-receiving-help-at-mozilla/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2018-01-giving-and-receiving-help-at-mozilla</guid>
   <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 18:49:34 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;This is going to sound corny, but helping people really is one of my favorite things at Mozilla, even with &lt;a href="https://mozilla.github.io/mozregression/"&gt;projects I have mostly moved on from&lt;/a&gt;. As someone who primarily works on internal tools, I love hearing about bugs in the software I maintain or questions on how to use it best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this, you might think that getting in touch with me via irc or slack is the fastest and best way to get your issue addressed. We certainly have a culture of using these instant-messaging applications at Mozilla for everything and anything. Unfortunately, I have found that being &amp;ldquo;always on&amp;rdquo; to respond to everything hasn&amp;rsquo;t been positive for either my productivity or mental health. My personal situation aside, getting pinged on irc while I&amp;rsquo;m out of the office often results in stuff getting lost &amp;mdash; the person who asked me the question is often gone by the time I return and am able to answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, here&amp;rsquo;s some notes on my preferred conversation style when making initial contact about an issue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Please don&amp;rsquo;t send context-free pings on irc. It has been &lt;a href="http://edunham.net/2017/10/05/saying_ping.html"&gt;explained elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;  why this doesn&amp;rsquo;t work that well, so I won&amp;rsquo;t repeat the argument here.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;If you are at all suspicious that your issue might be a bug in some software  maintain, just &lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/enter_bug.cgi"&gt;file a bug&lt;/a&gt; and needinfo me. That puts us right on the path to documenting  the problem and getting to a resolution &amp;mdash; even if something turns out to not  be a bug, if you&amp;rsquo;re seeing an unexpected error it points to a usability issue.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;For everything else, email is best. I do check it quite frequently between  bursts of work (i.e. many times a day). I promise I won&amp;rsquo;t leave you hanging  for days on end as long as I&amp;rsquo;m not on vacation.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These aren&amp;rsquo;t ironclad rules. If your question pertains to a project I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;em&gt;actively&lt;/em&gt; working on, it might make sense to ping me on irc first (preferably on a channel where other people are around who might also be able to help). If it&amp;rsquo;s an actual &lt;em&gt;emergency&lt;/em&gt;, then of course talk to me on irc straight away (or even call me on my phone) &amp;mdash; if I don&amp;rsquo;t respond, then fall back to filing bug or sending email. Use common sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my new years resolutions is to also apply these rules to my communications with others at Mozilla as well, so if you see my violating it feel free to point me back at this post. Or just use this handy meme I created:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src="/files/2018/01/scale-of-asking.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Maintaining metricsgraphics</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2017/12/maintaining-metricsgraphics/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2017-12-maintaining-metricsgraphics</guid>
   <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 22:16:23 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Just a quick announcement that I&amp;rsquo;ve taken it upon myself to assume some maintership duties of the popular &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/metrics-graphics"&gt;MetricsGraphics&lt;/a&gt; library and have released a &lt;a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/metrics-graphics"&gt;new version&lt;/a&gt; with some bug fixes (2.12.0). We use this package pretty extensively at Mozilla for visualizing telemetry and other time series data, but its original authors (Hamilton Ulmer and Ali Almossawi) have mostly moved on to other things so there was a bit of a gap in getting fixes and improvements in that I hope to fill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t yet claim to be an expert in this library (which is quite rich and complex), but I&amp;rsquo;m sure I&amp;rsquo;ll learn more as I go along. At least initially, I expect that the changes I make will be small and primarily targetted to filling the needs of the &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/missioncontrol"&gt;Mission Control&lt;/a&gt; project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this emphatically does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; mean I am promising to respond to every issue/question/pull request made against the project. Like my work with mozregression and perfherder, my maintenance work is being done on a best-effort basis to support Mozilla and the larger open source community. I&amp;rsquo;ll help people out where I can, but there are only so many working hours in a day and I need to spend most of those pushing my team&amp;rsquo;s immediate projects and deliverables forward! In particular, when it comes to getting pull requests merged, small, self-contained and logical changes with good commit messages will take priority.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Better or worse: by what measure?</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2017/10/better-or-worse-by-what-measure/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2017-10-better-or-worse-by-what-measure</guid>
   <pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2017 20:58:20 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Ok, after a series of posts extolling the virtues of my current project, it&amp;rsquo;s time to take a more critical look at some of its current limitations, and what we might do about them. In my &lt;a href="/blog/2017/10/mission-control/"&gt;introductory post&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about how Mission Control can let us know how &amp;ldquo;crashy&amp;rdquo; a new release is, within a short interval of it being released. I also alluded to the fact that things appear considerably worse when something first goes out, though I didn&amp;rsquo;t go into a lot of detail about how and why that happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It just so happens that a new point release (56.0.2) just went out, so it&amp;rsquo;s a perfect opportunity to revisit this issue. Let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at what the graphs are saying (each of the images is also a link to the dashboard where they were generated):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://data-missioncontrol.dev.mozaws.net/#/release/windows/content_crashes?timeInterval=172740&amp;amp;percentile=99&amp;amp;normalized=1&amp;amp;disabledVersions=&amp;amp;versionGrouping=version&amp;amp;startTime=1508990400"&gt;&lt;img srcset="/files/2017/10/missioncontrol_windows_content_crashes_56.0.2.png 2x" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ZOMG! It looks like 56.0.2 is off the charts relative to the two previous releases (56.0 and 56.0.1). Is it time to sound the alarm? Mission control abort? Well, let&amp;rsquo;s see what happens the last time we rolled something new out, say 56.0.1:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://data-missioncontrol.dev.mozaws.net/#/release/windows/content_crashes?timeInterval=345540&amp;amp;percentile=99&amp;amp;normalized=1&amp;amp;disabledVersions=&amp;amp;versionGrouping=version&amp;amp;startTime=1507435200"&gt;&lt;img srcset="/files/2017/10/missioncontrol_windows_content_crashes_56.0.1.png 2x" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see the exact same pattern. Hmm. How about 56.0?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://data-missioncontrol.dev.mozaws.net/#/release/windows/content_crashes?timeInterval=431940&amp;amp;percentile=99&amp;amp;normalized=1&amp;amp;disabledVersions=&amp;amp;versionGrouping=version&amp;amp;startTime=1506398400"&gt;&lt;img srcset="/files/2017/10/missioncontrol_windows_content_crashes_56.png 2x" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yep, same pattern here too (actually slightly worse).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What could be going on? Let&amp;rsquo;s start by reviewing what these time series graphs are based on. Each point on the graph represents the number of crashes reported by telemetry &amp;ldquo;main&amp;rdquo; pings corresponding to that channel/version/platform within a five minute interval, divided by the number of usage hours (how long users have had Firefox open) also reported in that interval. A main ping is submitted under &lt;a href="https://firefox-source-docs.mozilla.org/toolkit/components/telemetry/telemetry/data/main-ping.html"&gt;a few circumstances&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;The user shuts down Firefox&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;It’s been about 24 hours since the last time we sent a main ping.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;The user starts Firefox after Firefox failed to start properly&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;The user changes something about Firefox’s environment (adds an addon, flips a user preference)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A high crash rate either means a larger number of crashes over the same number of usage hours, or a lower number of usage hours over the same number of crashes. There are several likely explanations for why we might see this type of crashy behaviour immediately after a new release:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;A Firefox update is applied after the user restarts their browser for any  reason, including their browser crash. Thus a user whose browser crashes a  lot (for any reason), is more prone to update to the latest version sooner  than a user that doesn’t crash as much.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Inherently, any crash data submitted to telemetry after a new version is  released will have a low number of usage hours attached, because the  client would not have had a chance to use it much (because it&amp;rsquo;s so new).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming that we&amp;rsquo;re reasonably satisfied with the above explanation, there&amp;rsquo;s a few things we could try to do to correct for this situation when implementing an &amp;ldquo;alerting&amp;rdquo; system for mission control (the next item on my todo list for this project):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Set &amp;ldquo;error&amp;rdquo; thresholds for each crash measure sufficiently high that  we don&amp;rsquo;t consider these high initial values an error (i.e. only alert  if there is are 500 crashes per 1k hours).&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Only trigger an error threshold when some kind of minimum quantity of  usage hours has been observed (this has the disadvantage of potentially  obscuring a serious problem until a large percentage of the user population  is affected by it).&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Come up with some expected range of what we expect a value to be for  when a new version of firefox is first released and ratchet  that down as time goes on (according to some kind of model of our previous expectations).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial specification for this project called for just using raw thresholds for these measures (discounting usage hours), but I&amp;rsquo;m becoming increasingly convinced that won&amp;rsquo;t cut it. I&amp;rsquo;m not a quality control expert, but 500 crashes for 1k hours of use sounds completely unacceptable if we&amp;rsquo;re measuring things at all accurately (which I believe we are given a sufficient period of time). At the same time, generating 20&amp;ndash;30 “alerts” every time a new release went out wouldn’t particularly helpful either. Once again, we’re going to have to do this the hard way&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this sounds interesting and you have some react/d3/data visualization skills (or would like to gain some), &lt;a href="/blog/2017/10/mission-control-ready-for-contributions/"&gt;learn about contributing to mission control&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shout out to &lt;a href="https://chuttenblog.wordpress.com/"&gt;chutten&lt;/a&gt; for reviewing this post and providing feedback and additions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Mission Control: Ready for contributions</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2017/10/mission-control-ready-for-contributions/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2017-10-mission-control-ready-for-contributions</guid>
   <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 18:33:19 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;One of the great design decisions that was made for &lt;a href="https://treeherder.mozilla.org"&gt;Treeherder&lt;/a&gt; was a strict seperation of the client and server portions of the codebase. While its backend was moderately complicated to get up and running (especially into a state that looked at all like what we were running in production), you could get its web frontend running (pointed against the production data) just by starting up a simple node.js server. This dramatically lowered the barrier to entry, for Mozilla employees and casual contributors alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew right from the beginning that I wanted to take the same approach with &lt;a href="https://wlach.github.io/blog/2017/10/mission-control/"&gt;Mission Control&lt;/a&gt;. While the full source of the project is available, unfortunately it isn&amp;rsquo;t presently possible to bring up the full stack with real data, as that requires privileged access to the athena/parquet error aggregates table. But since the UI is self-contained, it&amp;rsquo;s quite easy to bring up a development environment that allows you to freely browse the cached data which is stored server-side (essentially: &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/mozilla/missioncontrol.git &amp;amp;&amp;amp; yarn install &amp;amp;&amp;amp; yarn start&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, the most interesting problems when it comes to projects like these center around the question of how to present extremely complex data in a way that is intuitive but not misleading. Probably 90% of that work happens in the frontend. In the past, I&amp;rsquo;ve had pretty good luck finding contributors for my projects (especially &lt;a href="/tags/Perfherder.html"&gt;Perfherder&lt;/a&gt;) by doing call-outs on this blog. So let it be known: If Mission Control sounds like an interesting project and you know &lt;a href="https://reactjs.org/"&gt;React&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="http://redux.js.org/"&gt;Redux&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="https://d3js.org/"&gt;D3&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="https://www.metricsgraphicsjs.org/"&gt;MetricsGraphics&lt;/a&gt; (or want to learn), let&amp;rsquo;s work together!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve created some &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/missioncontrol/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3A%22good+first+issue%22"&gt;good first bugs&lt;/a&gt; to tackle in the github issue tracker. From there, I have a galaxy of other work in mind to improve and enhance the usefulness of this project. Please get in touch with me (wlach) on &lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/IRC"&gt;irc.mozilla.org&lt;/a&gt; #missioncontrol if you want to discuss further.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Mission Control</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2017/10/mission-control/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2017-10-mission-control</guid>
   <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 19:05:37 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Time for an overdue post on the mission control project that I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on for the past few quarters, since I transitioned to the data platform team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the gaps in our data story when it comes to Firefox is being able to see how a new release is doing in the immediate hours after release. Tools like &lt;a href="https://crash-stats.mozilla.com/home/product/Firefox"&gt;crashstats&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://telemetry.mozilla.org/new-pipeline/evo.html"&gt;telemetry evolution dashboard&lt;/a&gt; are great, but it can take many hours (if not days) before you can reliably see that there is an issue in a metric that we care about (number of crashes, say). This is just too long &amp;mdash; such delays unnecessarily retard rolling out a release when it is safe (because there is a paranoia that there might be some lingering problem which we we&amp;rsquo;re waiting to see reported). And if, somehow, despite our abundant caution a problem &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; slip through it would take us some time to recognize it and roll out a fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter mission control. By hooking up a high-performance spark streaming job directly to our ingestion pipeline, we can now be able to detect within moments whether firefox is performing unacceptably within the field according to a particular measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the volume of data manageable, we create a grouped data set with the raw count of the various measures (e.g. main crashes, content crashes, slow script dialog counts) along with each unique combination of dimensions (e.g. platform, channel, release).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, all this data is not so useful without a tool to visualize it, which is what I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending the majority of my time on. The idea is to be able to go from a top level description of what&amp;rsquo;s going on a particular channel (release for example) all the way down to a detailed view of how a measure has been performing over a time interval:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img srcset="/files/2017/10/missioncontrol-ui.png 2x" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular screenshot shows the volume of content crashes (sampled every 5 minutes) over the last 48 hours on windows release. You&amp;rsquo;ll note that the later version (56.0) seems to be much crashier than earlier versions (55.0.3) which would seem to be a problem except that the populations are not directly comparable (since the profile of a user still on an older version of Firefox is rather different from that of one who has already upgraded). This is one of the still unsolved problems of this project: finding a reliable, automatable baseline of what an &amp;ldquo;acceptable result&amp;rdquo; for any particular measure might be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even still, the tool can still be useful for exploring a bunch of data quickly and it has been progressing rapidly over the last few weeks. And like almost everything Mozilla does, both the &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/missioncontrol/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://data-missioncontrol.dev.mozaws.net/"&gt;dashboard&lt;/a&gt; are open to the public. I&amp;rsquo;m planning on flagging some easier bugs for newer contributors to work on in the next couple weeks, but in the meantime if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in this project and want to get involved, feel free to look us up on irc.mozilla.org #missioncontrol (I&amp;rsquo;m there as &amp;lsquo;wlach&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Functional is the future</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2017/08/functional-is-the-future/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2017-08-functional-is-the-future</guid>
   <pubDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2017 21:02:21 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Just spent well over an hour tracking down a silly bug in my code. For the &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/missioncontrol/"&gt;mission control&lt;/a&gt; project, I wrote this very simple API method that returns a cached data structure to our front end:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: py"&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def measure(request):
    channel_name = request.GET.get('channel')
    platform_name = request.GET.get('platform')
    measure_name = request.GET.get('measure')
    interval = request.GET.get('interval')
    if not all([channel_name, platform_name, measure_name]):
        return HttpResponseBadRequest("All of channel, platform, measure required")
    data = cache.get(get_measure_cache_key(platform_name, channel_name, measure_name))
    if not data:
        return HttpResponseNotFound("Data not available for this measure combination")
    if interval:
        try:
            min_time = datetime.datetime.now() - datetime.timedelta(seconds=int(interval))
        except ValueError:
            return HttpResponseBadRequest("Interval must be specified in seconds (as an integer)")

        # Return any build data in the interval
        empty_buildids = set()
        for (build_id, build_data) in data.items():
            build_data['data'] = [d for d in build_data['data'] if d[0] &amp;gt; min_time]
            if not build_data['data']:
                empty_buildids.add(build_id)

        # don't bother returning empty indexed data
        for empty_buildid in empty_buildids:
            del data[empty_buildid]

    return JsonResponse(data={'measure_data': data})&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, it takes 3 required parameters (channel, platform, and measure) and one optional one (interval), picks out the required data structure, filters it a bit, and returns it. This is &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; what we wanted for the frontend, unfortunately the time zone information isn&amp;rsquo;t quite what we want, since the strings that are returned don&amp;rsquo;t tell the frontend that they&amp;rsquo;re in UTC format &amp;mdash; they need a &amp;lsquo;Z&amp;rsquo; appended to them for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a bit of digging, I found out that Django&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://github.com/django/django/blob/afc06b56256f78ab832ff8066ac6f34b7443de22/django/core/serializers/json.py#L76"&gt;json serializer&lt;/a&gt; will only add the Z if the tzinfo structure is specified. So I figured out a simple pattern for adding that (using the dateutil library, which we are fortunately already using):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: py"&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from dateutil.tz import tzutc
datetime.datetime.fromtimestamp(mydatestamp.timestamp(), tz=tzutc())&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tested this quickly on the python console and it seemed to work great. But when I added the code to my function, the unit tests mysteriously failed. Can you see why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: py"&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;for (build_id, build_data) in data.items():
    # add utc timezone info to each date, so django will serialize a
    # 'Z' to the end of the string (and so javascript's date constructor
    # will know it's utc)
    build_data['data'] = [
        [datetime.datetime.fromtimestamp(d[0].timestamp(), tz=tzutc())] + d[1:] for
        d in build_data['data'] if d[0] &amp;gt; min_time
    ]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trick question: there&amp;rsquo;s actually nothing wrong with this code. But if you look at the block in context (see the top of the post), you see that it&amp;rsquo;s only executed if &lt;em&gt;interval&lt;/em&gt; is specified, which it isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily. The first case that my unit tests executed didn&amp;rsquo;t specify interval, so fail they did. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t immediately obvious to me why this was happening, so I went on a wild-goose chase of trying to figure out how the Django context might have been responsible for the unexpected output, before realizing my basic logic error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was fairly easily corrected (my updated code applies the datetime-mapping unconditionally to set of optionally-filtered results) but perfectly illustrates my issue with idiomatic python: while the language itself has constructs like &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;reduce&lt;/code&gt; that support the functional programming model, the language strongly steers you towards writing things in an imperative style that makes costly and annoying mistakes like this much easier to make. Yes, list and dictionary comprehensions are nice and compact but they start to break down in the more complex cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an experiment, I wrote up what this function might look like in a pure functional style with immutable data structures:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: py"&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def transform_and_filter_data(build_data):
    new_build_data = copy.copy(build_data)
    new_build_data['data'] = [
        [datetime.datetime.fromtimestamp(d[0].timestamp(), tz=tzutc())] + d[1:] for
        d in build_data['data'] if d[0] &amp;gt; min_time
    ]
    return new_build_data
transformed_build_data = {k: v for k, v in {k: transform_and_filter_data(v) for k, v in data}.items() if len(v['data']) &amp;gt; 0}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A work of art it isn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;mdash; and definitely not &amp;ldquo;pythonic&amp;rdquo;. Compare this to a similar piece of code written in Javascript (ES6) with lodash (using a hypothetical &lt;code&gt;tzified&lt;/code&gt; function):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: js"&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;let transformedBuildData = _.filter(_.mapValues(data, (buildData) =&amp;gt; ({
    ...buildData,
    data: buildData.data
      .filter(datum =&amp;gt; datum[0] &amp;gt; minTimestamp)
      .map(datum =&amp;gt; [tzcified(datum[0])].concat(datum.slice(1)))
  })),
  (data, buildId) =&amp;gt; data.data.length &amp;gt; 0);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little bit easier to understand, but more importantly (to me anyway) it comes across as idiomatic and natural in a way that the python version just doesn&amp;rsquo;t. I&amp;rsquo;ve been happily programming Python for the last 10 years, but it&amp;rsquo;s increasingly feeling time to move on to greener pastures.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>mozregression's new mascot</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2017/07/mozregression-s-new-mascot/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2017-07-mozregression-s-new-mascot</guid>
   <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 15:32:02 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Spent a few hours this morning on a few housekeeping issues with &lt;a href="https://mozilla.github.io/mozregression"&gt;mozregression&lt;/a&gt;. The web site was badly in need of an update (it was full of references to obsolete stuff like B2G and codefirefox.com) and the usual pile of fixes motivated a new release of the actual software. But most importantly, mozregression now has a proper application icon / logo, thanks to Victoria Wang!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/files/2017/07/mozregressionicon3.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the nice parts about working at Mozilla is the flexibility it offers to just hack on stuff that&amp;rsquo;s important, whether or not it&amp;rsquo;s part of your formal job description. Maintaining mozregression is pretty far outside my current set of responsibilities (or even interests), but I keep it going because it&amp;rsquo;s a key tool used by developers team here and no one else seems willing to take it over. Fortunately, tools like appveyor and pypi keep the time suckage to a mostly-reasonable level.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Taking over an npm package: sanity prevails</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2017/07/taking-over-an-npm-package-sanity-prevails/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2017-07-taking-over-an-npm-package-sanity-prevails</guid>
   <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2017 15:08:40 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes problems are easier to solve than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last few months I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on the front end of a new project called &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/missioncontrol"&gt;Mission Control&lt;/a&gt;, which aims to chart lots of interesting live information in something approximating realtime. Since this is a greenfield project, I thought it would make sense to use the currently-invogue framework at Mozilla (react) along with our standard visualization library, &lt;a href="http://metricsgraphicsjs.org/"&gt;metricsgraphics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metricsgraphics is great, but its jquery-esque api is somewhat at odds with the react way. The obvious solution to this problem is to wrap its functionality in a react component, and a quick google search determined that several people have tried to do exactly that, the most popular one being one called (obviously) react-metrics-graphics. Unfortunately, it hadn&amp;rsquo;t been updated in quite some time and some pull requests (including ones implementing features I needed for my project) weren&amp;rsquo;t being responded to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expected this to be pretty difficult to resolve: I had no interaction with the author (Carter Feldman) before but based on my past experiences in free software, I was expecting stonewalling, leaving me no choice but to fork the package and give it a new name, a rather unsatisfying end result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, hey, let&amp;rsquo;s keep an open mind on this. What does google say about unmaintained npm packages? Oh what&amp;rsquo;s this? They actually have a &lt;a href="https://docs.npmjs.com/misc/disputes"&gt;policy&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;tl;dr: You email the maintainer (politely) and CC support@npmjs.org about your interest in helping maintain the software. If you&amp;rsquo;re unable to come up with a resolution on your own, they will intervene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I tried that. It turns out that Carter was really happy to hear that Mozilla was interested in taking over maintenance of this project, and not only gave me permission to start publishing newer versions to npm, but even transferred his repository over to Mozilla (so we could preserve issue and PR history). The project&amp;rsquo;s new location is here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/react-metrics-graphics"&gt;https://github.com/mozilla/react-metrics-graphics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, this is obviously the most reasonable outcome and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure why I was expecting anything else. Is the node community just friendlier than other areas I&amp;rsquo;ve worked in? Have community standards improved generally? In any case, thank you Carter for a great piece of software, hopefully it will thrive in its new home. :P&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Using Docker to run automated tests</title>
   <link>https://wlach.github.io/blog/2017/06/using-docker-to-run-automated-tests/?utm_source=Mozilla&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2017-06-using-docker-to-run-automated-tests</guid>
   <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 20:04:38 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;A couple months ago, I joined the Mozilla Data Platform team, to work on our &lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Telemetry"&gt;Telemetry&lt;/a&gt; and automated data collection services. This has been an interesting transition for me, and a natural jumping off point from my work on &lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/EngineeringProductivity/Projects/Perfherder"&gt;Perfherder&lt;/a&gt;. Now, instead of manipulating mere 10s of gigabytes worth of fairly regular data, I&amp;rsquo;m working with 100s of terrabytes of noisy data with a much larger number of dimensions. :P It&amp;rsquo;s been interesting so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first things I decided to work on was improving our unit testing story around a few of our primary packages for data analysis/etl: &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/python_moztelemetry/"&gt;python_moztelemetry&lt;/a&gt; (a library we use for running custom spark jobs against Telemetry data) and &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/telemetry-batch-view/"&gt;telemetry-batch-view&lt;/a&gt; (a set of scala jobs we run against the main telemetry data store to create a useful set of aggregations that are easily queried with tools like &lt;a href="https://redash.io/"&gt;redash&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that these tools interact with several larger / more involved pieces than I&amp;rsquo;m used to dealing with (such as hbase and thrift). For continuous integration/automation, we already had a set of travis scripts to install and reproduce the environment needed to test these parts, but there was no straightforward way to do this locally. My third time through creating an Ubuntu virtual machine environment to reproduce this environment locally (long story), I figured it was finally time for me to investigate using something to automate that setup procedure and make it easier for new developers to get into these projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t used it much before, but &lt;a href="https://docker.com"&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; seemed like a fairly obvious choice. Small, simple, and Linuxy? Sign me up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m pretty happy with how things turned out, but there were a few caveats. Docker is more of a general purpose tool for building environments for running &lt;em&gt;things&lt;/em&gt;, whether that be an apache webserver or a jabber messaging doohickey (whereas e.g. something like travis is basically a domain-specific language for creating and running automated tests). There were a few tricks I needed to employ to make the whole testing process smooth in both cases, which I&amp;rsquo;ll document here for posterity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;You can &lt;code&gt;ADD&lt;/code&gt; a set of files / directories to a docker environment inside your Dockerfile, but if you want your set of tests to pick up any changes made since the environment was created, you really should mount your testing directory inside the container using the &lt;code&gt;-v&lt;/code&gt; option.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;If you need to download/install a piece of software when building the docker container, use the &lt;code&gt;RUN&lt;/code&gt; directive instead of &lt;code&gt;ADD&lt;/code&gt;. This will speed up rebuilding the container while you&amp;rsquo;re iterating on it (because you can take advantage of the Docker layers cache).&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;You almost certainly want to create a script (&lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/python_moztelemetry/blob/d2aa84bbac09465d38eeb0b5beb20edc7ddcc21b/runtests.sh"&gt;example&lt;/a&gt;) to streamline all the steps of running the tests: this will make running the tests easier for anyone wanting to contribute to your project and reduce the amount of documentation that you will have to write.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relevant files and documentation are in the repositories linked above.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>