<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<rss version="2.0">
 <channel>
  <title>William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Music'</title>
  <description>William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Music'</description>
  <link>https://wrla.ch/tags/Music.html</link>
  <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 20:02:06 UT</lastBuildDate>
  <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 20:02:06 UT</pubDate>
  <ttl>1800</ttl>
  <item>
   <title>Rethinking Music Listening</title>
   <link>https://wrla.ch/blog/2026/01/rethinking-music-listening/?utm_source=Music&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wrla-ch:-blog-2026-01-rethinking-music-listening</guid>
   <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 20:02:06 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;On this day in 2026, I canceled my Spotify subscription. This was a long time coming, but what finally pushed me over the edge was listening to this podcast on streaming services a couple weeks ago:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://techwontsave.us/episode/262_how_spotify_remade_the_music_industry_w_liz_pelly"&gt;How Spotify Remade the Music Industry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I lament the loss of place that music has had in my life over the last decade. It&amp;rsquo;s probably unfair to say that streaming services were the sole cause of this: aging and changes in circumstance clearly played a role. That said, I don&amp;rsquo;t think they&amp;rsquo;ve helped, and I want to try a different approach to music listening with a bit of deliberate friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;ve done:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Revived my archive of music from ~2009, just before I started streaming seriously. Was lucky enough to have an old hard drive laying around (that immediately died after the transfer).&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Bought a bunch of music on &lt;a href="https://bandcamp.com/"&gt;Bandcamp&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;d been listening to recently direct from the artist / label, downloaded AAC versions.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Installed &lt;a href="https://syncthing.net/"&gt;Syncthing&lt;/a&gt; to share said folder between my Linux laptop, my work (Mac) laptop and my Pixel 8 phone (cool software!)&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Installed &lt;a href="https://krosbits.in/musicolet/"&gt;Musicolet&lt;/a&gt; on my Pixel&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Installed &lt;a href="https://brushedtype.co/doppler/"&gt;Doppler&lt;/a&gt; on my Mac (much of my legacy CD collection was transcoded to Ogg Vorbis, which iTunes doesn&amp;rsquo;t support). For Linux, I&amp;rsquo;m just going to use Rhythmbox for a while and see how it goes.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, so good? I&amp;rsquo;m still listening to music at least. Various one-time expenses incurred for new software and I expect Bandcamp will be an ongoing one (which will definitely exceed what I paid for a Spotify subscription up to now), but feels worth it as long as I can afford it.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Rice &amp;#038; Barley, Rae Spoon at Casa del Popolo</title>
   <link>https://wrla.ch/blog/2010/11/rice-038-barley-rae-spoon-at-casa-del-popolo/?utm_source=Music&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wrla-ch:-blog-2010-11-rice-038-barley-rae-spoon-at-casa-del-popolo</guid>
   <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2010 05:00:00 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;This weekend my girlfriend&amp;rsquo;s band (Rice &amp;#38; Barley) did a show at Casa del Popolo. It was great, you should have been there. I made some videos using my trusty new iPhone:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.raespoon.com/"&gt;Rae Spoon&lt;/a&gt;, the headline act, was awesome. I recorded one of his songs, which he kindly gave permission to post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vidya (the other opening band) was good too, though I didn&amp;rsquo;t get a chance to record them. Next time!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>