<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
 <title type="text">William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Nixi'</title>
 <link rel="self" href="https://wlach.github.io/feeds/Nixi.atom.xml" />
 <link href="https://wlach.github.io/tags/Nixi.html" />
 <id>urn:https-wlach-github-io:-tags-Nixi-html</id>
 <updated>2016-01-09T04:21:13Z</updated>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">NIXI is moving too</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://wlach.github.io/blog/2016/01/nixi-is-moving-too/?utm_source=Nixi&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2016-01-nixi-is-moving-too</id>
  <published>2016-01-09T04:21:13Z</published>
  <updated>2016-01-09T04:21:13Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>William Lachance</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As my blog goes to github pages, so do my other side projects. I just moved nixi, my bikestation finder project, to github pages. Its new location:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wlach.github.io/nixi"&gt;http://wlach.github.io/nixi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I opted not to move over the domain: it would have cost extra money, time and hassle and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t justify it for the very, very small number of people that still use this site (yes, there are a few, including myself!). For now, nixi.ca will redirect to the github pages site until I decommision my linode server, probably at the end of January (end of Feburary at the latest).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This transition brings some other changes with it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Now using the &lt;a href="https://citybik.es"&gt;citybik.es&lt;/a&gt; API directly,  instead of proxing through an intermediary server. This was necessitated  by the switch to github pages, but I suspect this will be more reliable  than what we were doing before. Thanks citybik.es!&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Removed all analytics and facebook integration. As with the domain, it didn&amp;rsquo;t  seem worth bringing over. Also, it&amp;rsquo;s nice to give people at least marginally  more privacy than they had before where possible.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still think nixi is worlds more usable than most bikesharing maps, even if it&amp;rsquo;s not an actively maintained project of mine any more. Here&amp;rsquo;s hoping it lasts many more years in its new incarnation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">NIXI Update</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://wlach.github.io/blog/2013/08/nixi-update/?utm_source=Nixi&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2013-08-nixi-update</id>
  <published>2013-08-25T04:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2013-08-25T04:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>William Lachance</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been working on a new, mobile friendly version of &lt;a href="http://nixi.ca/"&gt;Nixi&lt;/a&gt; on-and-off for the past year and a bit. I&amp;#8217;m not sure when it&amp;#8217;s ever going to be finished, so I thought I might as well post the work-in-progress, which has these noteworthy improvements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Even faster than before (using the &lt;a href="http://getbootstrap.com"&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; library behind the scenes, no longer using slow canvas library to update map)&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Sexier graphics (thanks to the aforementioned Bootstrap library)&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Now uses client side URLs to keep track of state as you navigate through the site. This allows you to bookmark a favorite spot (e.g. your home) and then go back to it later. For example, &lt;a href="http://nixi.ca/#/cities/montreal/places/5605%20avenue%20de%20Gaspe"&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt; will give you a list of BIXI docks near &lt;a href="http://www.station-c.com/"&gt;Station C&lt;/a&gt;, the coworking space I belong to.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use &lt;a href="http://bixi.com"&gt;BIXI&lt;/a&gt; at all, check it out and let me know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/files/2013/08/nixi-screenshot.png"&gt; &lt;img src="/files/2013/08/nixi-screenshot-1024x672.png" alt="nixi screenshot" width="640" height="420" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-927" srcset="/files/2013/08/nixi-screenshot-300x196.png 300w, /files/2013/08/nixi-screenshot-1024x672.png 1024w, /files/2013/08/nixi-screenshot.png 1266w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry></feed>