<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
 <title type="text">William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Orangutan'</title>
 <link rel="self" href="https://wlach.github.io/feeds/Orangutan.atom.xml" />
 <link href="https://wlach.github.io/tags/Orangutan.html" />
 <id>urn:https-wlach-github-io:-tags-Orangutan-html</id>
 <updated>2012-07-10T04:00:00Z</updated>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">The evolution of simulating events in Eideticker: from monkeys to orangutans</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://wlach.github.io/blog/2012/07/the-evolution-of-simulating-events-in-eideticker-from-monkeys-to-orangutans?utm_source=Orangutan&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2012-07-the-evolution-of-simulating-events-in-eideticker-from-monkeys-to-orangutans</id>
  <published>2012-07-10T04:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2012-07-10T04:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>William Lachance</name></author>
  <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[ For more information on the Eideticker software I&amp;#8217;m referring to, see &lt;a href="http://wrla.ch/blog/2012/06/mobile-firefox-measuring-how-a-browser-feels/"&gt;this entry&lt;/a&gt; ]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just merged a new approach I&amp;#8217;ve been using to simulate touch events into the master branch of Eideticker called &lt;a href="http://github.com/wlach/orangutan"&gt;Orangutan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wrla.ch/blog/2012/07/the-evolution-of-simulating-events-in-eideticker-from-monkeys-to-orangutns/orangutan/" rel="attachment wp-att-696"&gt;&lt;img src="/files/2012/07/orangutan.jpg" alt="Image of Orangutan" title="orangutan" width="415" height="600" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-696" srcset="/files/2012/07/orangutan-207x300.jpg 207w, /files/2012/07/orangutan.jpg 415w" sizes="(max-width: 415px) 100vw, 415px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;#8217;ve mentioned before, we really need to simulate actual user gestures when doing this type of testing to measure real-world performance with Eideticker. Up to now, I&amp;#8217;ve been using google&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://developer.android.com/tools/help/monkeyrunner_concepts.html"&gt;MonkeyRunner&lt;/a&gt; tool to do this. I was always a little skeptical about its approach (which involved using a privileged tool written in Java with special access to Android&amp;#8217;s windowing system), but up until recently I&amp;#8217;d managed to get around its &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/p/android/issues/detail?id=27955"&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; with a &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/eideticker/commit/8d034212bc38c1fc80b9fe792c0b06919c74141a"&gt;successively&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/eideticker/commit/55d63960dc0a5090cee00fe917a851db082ee0fd"&gt;more&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/eideticker/commit/686882d32fb25a700afec35c39e53a73658688e3"&gt;complicated&lt;/a&gt; series of hacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I finally came up with a problem that I couldn&amp;#8217;t figure out how to fix: monkeyrunner doesn&amp;#8217;t attach precise timing information to the events it generates, which completely throws off Google Chrome for Android when you try to simulate a pan gesture. I&amp;#8217;ve tried just about every way of using the existing functionality (both the networked mode and the &amp;#8220;script&amp;#8221; mode), but nothing seemed to help. My conclusion is that the only way of continuing to use monkey would be to create a fix for the software itself, which implies forking and extending the entire Android Open Source Project. As noble a goal as that might be, doing that across all the major Android versions I want to support (2.2, 2.3, 4.0 and now 4.1) was more work than I felt like taking on (not to mention the question of how to deploy that work). I decided to build something entirely new which did not have this requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter Orangutan. Unlike MonkeyRunner, Orangutan simply injects events directly into low-level the kernel device file that represents an Android device&amp;#8217;s touch screen. It&amp;#8217;s fast (written in native C), trivial to build, and seems to work seamlessly with any application I&amp;#8217;ve tried using it with (including Google Chrome for Android). Most interestingly for Mozilla, this interface is also present on Firefox OS (&lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/B2G"&gt;Boot to Gecko&lt;/a&gt;) based devices, so we should be able to use Orangutan there to support both Eideticker and any other testing framework which needs to test real-world user input test cases. Exciting times!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>