<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
 <title type="text">William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Pandaboard'</title>
 <link rel="self" href="https://wlach.github.io/feeds/Pandaboard.atom.xml" />
 <link href="https://wlach.github.io/tags/Pandaboard.html" />
 <id>urn:https-wlach-github-io:-tags-Pandaboard-html</id>
 <updated>2012-02-10T05:00:00Z</updated>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Playing with pandas</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://wlach.github.io/blog/2012/02/playing-with-pandas/?utm_source=Pandaboard&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:https-wlach-github-io:-blog-2012-02-playing-with-pandas</id>
  <published>2012-02-10T05:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2012-02-10T05:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>William Lachance</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last few days I&amp;#8217;ve been experimenting with getting a Pandaboard running Android 4.0, continuing the work that Clint Talbert &lt;a href="http://cmtalbert.wordpress.com/2011/10/12/pandaboard-status/"&gt;started in the fall&lt;/a&gt; to get these boards for use as a replacement for the Tegra in Mozilla&amp;#8217;s android automation. The first objective is to get a reproducible build going, after that we&amp;#8217;ll try to get some of our custom tools (&lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Mobile/Fennec_Unittests/Remote_Testing"&gt;SUTAgent&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#38; friends) installed by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far this has been&amp;#8230; interesting. Much as Clint did before, I thought I&amp;#8217;d document some of the notes on what I did in the hopes that they&amp;#8217;ll be helpful to other people trying to do similar things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting things up and running is a two step process. First, you build the beast. This part is straightforward, just follow the instructions here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least the build part is more or less straightforward. Just follow the instructions here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://source.android.com/source/building.html"&gt;http://source.android.com/source/building.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://source.android.com/source/building-devices.html"&gt;http://source.android.com/source/building-devices.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that you almost certainly want to build in the &amp;#8220;eng&amp;#8221; configuration, which is rooted and (apparently) has some extra tools installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing it is a little more tricky. The way they want you to do this is put the pandaboard into a special mode and copy the stuff you built onto an sdcard. Seem a little funny to you? Yeah, it does to me too. Why not just build an sdcard image directly?
 &lt;br /&gt;Nonetheless, this is the officially supported way of imaging a pandaboard, so let&amp;#8217;s just follow it until we can think of a better way of doing things. The instructions for doing this on the pandaboard are located in the source tree here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a href="http://source-android.frandroid.com/device/ti/panda/README"&amp;gt;device/ti/panda/README&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are mostly correct as far as I can tell, but there&amp;#8217;s a few gotchas. First, you need to run the commands mentioned as root unless you&amp;#8217;ve configured USB to be configurable by your user. Second, most of those commands are not in the path by default so you&amp;#8217;ll need to specify the full path to e.g. the fastboot utility. The instructions &lt;a href="http://fosiao.com/node/19"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; cover these exception cases: I recommend following them instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing which neither document mentions is that you really need to make sure your sdcard is wiped completely clean before using fastboot. The &amp;#8220;oem format&amp;#8221; step only recreates the partition table, it doesn&amp;#8217;t delete any corrupted partitions. If you reboot while these are still in place, it will try to bring up your corrupted version of Android, not the fastboot console. I spent quite some time debugging why I couldn&amp;#8217;t properly flash the operating system before realizing this. Easiest way to get around this is to dd &lt;code&gt;/dev/zero&lt;/code&gt; onto the sdcard before beginning the flashing process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, while not strictly necessary to get something up and running, I recommend highly getting an HDMI monitor as well as a serialUSB adapter. The former is useful to see if your Android device actually successfully booted up, the latter is useful for debugging boot issues where you don&amp;#8217;t get that far (the serial console is always available from boot).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, after painfully learning about the above caveats, I have managed to get things mostly working. I can see the ICS homescreen on my attached HDMI monitor and interact with it if I attach a USB mouse. The one gotcha is that both ethernet and WIFI networking are totally broken. Plugging in an ethernet cable or connecting to a WIFI network seems to result in the machine randomly rebooting, with the logs saying nothing useful. Both of these things are ostensibly supposed to be working according to the latest I&amp;#8217;ve read from Google so I&amp;#8217;m not exactly sure what&amp;#8217;s going on. Investigations will continue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry></feed>