<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
 <title type="text">William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Personal'</title>
 <link rel="self" href="https://wrla.ch/feeds/Personal.atom.xml" />
 <link href="https://wrla.ch/tags/Personal.html" />
 <id>urn:https-wrla-ch:-tags-Personal-html</id>
 <updated>2022-11-26T15:24:01Z</updated>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Working with depression</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://wrla.ch/blog/2022/11/working-with-depression/?utm_source=Personal&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:https-wrla-ch:-blog-2022-11-working-with-depression</id>
  <published>2022-11-26T15:24:01Z</published>
  <updated>2022-11-26T15:24:01Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>William Lachance</name></author>
  <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Been struggling with depression over the past couple of weeks. Some of this is seasonal (with the shortening of the days), though I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t say it &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; happens. Last year at this time I recall feeling the &lt;em&gt;opposite&lt;/em&gt; of depressed: that probably had to do with the fact that I knew I was leaving my previous job at Mozilla and wanted to get as much done as possible. Sometimes a highly motivating life situation can keep it in abeyance. Nonetheless, it&amp;rsquo;s here now, again, and demands to be dealt with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does depression even mean? It&amp;rsquo;s a bit of a hard thing to pin down, exactly. But from the perspective of looking after my own well being, I don&amp;rsquo;t think I really need a definition. What matters are the symptoms, which I&amp;rsquo;d roughly express as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Knowing what I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be doing but not able to do it&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;An increase in time spent scanning social media, news sites&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Feelings of low self worth&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Feelings that nothing really matters&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Lack of creativity, improvisation&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;An increase in self-referential thinking (this post would be an example of that)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few things I tend to try to diminish its effects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Go outside, expose myself to sunlight. Explore nature.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Exercise&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Meditate&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Eat less carbohydrates, more vegetables and protein&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Talk to friends&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Do nice things for other people&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t feel like doing these things but I try with all my might, against all my will, to do them anyway. Any individual action might not do much: but the cumulative effect of doing &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the above seems to have an impact &amp;mdash; or at least that&amp;rsquo;s what I tell myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet despite my best efforts, it&amp;rsquo;s not always enough. I do all of the things in the second list, and yet still find myself suffering in all the ways described by the first. What do I do then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to understand that there really isn&amp;rsquo;t an escape from unpleasant feeling, and that it&amp;rsquo;s just part of life: glorious and beautiful in its complexity. I try to be &lt;em&gt;curious&lt;/em&gt; about what&amp;rsquo;s going on, even if I think it&amp;rsquo;s all happened before. If that&amp;rsquo;s not possible, I at least try to be present with it. That&amp;rsquo;s all I can do.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>