<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<rss version="2.0">
 <channel>
  <title>William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Toronto'</title>
  <description>William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Toronto'</description>
  <link>https://wrla.ch/tags/Toronto.html</link>
  <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 04:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
  <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 04:00:00 UT</pubDate>
  <ttl>1800</ttl>
  <item>
   <title>New city, new cellphone provider</title>
   <link>https://wrla.ch/blog/2014/07/new-city-new-cellphone-provider/?utm_source=Toronto&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wrla-ch:-blog-2014-07-new-city-new-cellphone-provider</guid>
   <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 04:00:00 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Rogers, my previous cell phone provider, is ridiculous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for those of you who don&amp;rsquo;t know, I just moved from Montreal to Toronto. There are very few people who call me these days, but some still do and keeping my old Montreal number subjects me to a bunch of long distance fees I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to pay every time someone dials my number while I&amp;rsquo;m here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really didn&amp;rsquo;t want to go to the trouble of changing my cellphone company, so was ready to just switch my number and keep my $60/mo. plan with Rogers. I knew it was kind of expensive, but they haven&amp;rsquo;t given me much trouble and I do put a premium on my time not being occupied with changing service providers. I also figured I had bigger fish to fry in terms of finding budgetary savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But no, apparently the &amp;ldquo;market&amp;rdquo; in Ontario is &amp;ldquo;less competitive&amp;rdquo;, so my plan doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist here. After an hour and several levels of polite escalation (in strict violation of the &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t waste my time&amp;rdquo; rule), the best they could give me was a $70/mo. plan (a $10 increase) with a decrease of 3gb data -&amp;gt; 2gb. I gave them plenty of opportunities to relent, but they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t budge. They claimed there was no reasonable alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did some shopping around: unfortunately Wind (the best value) didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to work with my Nexus 5, so I went with Virgin Mobile who looked like the next best option. Up and running in just half an hour, and will probably be paying no more than $50 a month now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what happened to the legendary Rogers customer retention department? How do they think they can get away charging these kinds of rates?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>