<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<rss version="2.0">
 <channel>
  <title>William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Transit to Go'</title>
  <description>William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Transit to Go'</description>
  <link>https://wrla.ch/tags/Transit-to-Go.html</link>
  <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2011 04:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2011 04:00:00 UT</pubDate>
  <ttl>1800</ttl>
  <item>
   <title>Routez opensourced</title>
   <link>https://wrla.ch/blog/2011/04/routez-opensourced/?utm_source=Transit-to-Go&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wrla-ch:-blog-2011-04-routez-opensourced</guid>
   <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2011 04:00:00 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;Just a quick note to say that I just opensourced the software behind &lt;a href="http://hbus.ca"&gt;hbus.ca&lt;/a&gt;, nicknamed &amp;ldquo;Routez&amp;rdquo; under the &lt;a href="http://www.affero.org/oagpl.html"&gt;Affero GPL&lt;/a&gt;. You can get the code on &lt;a href="http://github.com/wlach/routez"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wrla.ch/blog/2011/04/routez-opensourced/hbus_shot_apr_2011/" rel="attachment wp-att-238"&gt;&lt;img src="/files/2011/04/hbus_shot_apr_2011.png" alt="" title="hbus_shot_apr_2011" width="300" height="225" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-238" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those new to the project, hbus.ca is a generic trip planning / transit information site for Halifax, Nova Scotia written using the &lt;a href="http://www.django-project.com"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; web framework. It currently has two main features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;A trip planning front-end much like Google Transit (built from the ground up using the &lt;a href="http://github.com/wlach/libroutez"&gt;libroutez&lt;/a&gt; library).&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;A &amp;ldquo;nearby&amp;rdquo; routes feature which gives you all the bus departures near a particular location.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the backend, both of these features are accessible via JSON APIs, for use in transit apps, etc. &lt;a href="http://transittogo.mindsea.ca"&gt;Transit to Go&lt;/a&gt; uses these to great effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is nothing particularly Halifax-specific to the underlying Routez software, aside from various references in the web front end to Halifax and hbus.ca. In fact, we use Routez to provide information for Transit to Go Edmonton right now, with no modification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally my plan was to release something that was completely generic out of the box so that anyone could trivially make up a version of this site for their favourite city. I&amp;rsquo;ve made some headway towards that goal over the last week or so, but there&amp;rsquo;s still some ways to go. There&amp;rsquo;s basically two major issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;The geocoder depends on information gleaned from the geobase road network dataset. The intent behind this is noble (provide an end-to-end solution that doesn&amp;rsquo;t depend on third parties) but in practice this limits the software&amp;rsquo;s usefulness. It would be better to optionally allow a Routez-based site to use Google&amp;rsquo;s geocoder on the front-end. Unfortunately, to comply with Google&amp;rsquo;s terms of service, we&amp;rsquo;d also need to use their Maps API for the base map as well. Perhaps the best option here would be to use something like &lt;a href="http://mapstraction.com"&gt;Mapstraction&lt;/a&gt; to allow users to select their preferred mapping provider.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;The trip planning software used in the backend, libroutez, is getting a bit long in the tooth and is quite finicky about what kind of data it will accept. I think the long-term solution to this is to switch to &lt;a href="http://graphserver.github.com/graphserver/"&gt;Graphserver&lt;/a&gt; (which is more mature and better supported), but some features would have to be added to it to support the kind of things that Routez needs (like a list of upcoming departures at a particular transit stop).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with these problems, I figured it would be better to open up what I have for people to check out and play with. Have a look and let me know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>I can has Edmonton transit iPhone app?</title>
   <link>https://wrla.ch/blog/2010/04/i-can-has-edmonton-transit-iphone-app/?utm_source=Transit-to-Go&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wrla-ch:-blog-2010-04-i-can-has-edmonton-transit-iphone-app</guid>
   <pubDate>Sat, 10 Apr 2010 04:00:00 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/files/2010/04/t2go-edmonton-take1.png" alt="Transit to Go Edmonton take 1" title="Transit to Go Edmonton take 1" width="320" height="595" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-130" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href="http://wrla.ch/blog/2010/04/oh-the-lines-and-some-help-for-edmonton/"&gt;yesterday&amp;rsquo;s work&lt;/a&gt; out of the way, there weren&amp;rsquo;t too many extra steps required before I got a basic version of Transit to Go running for Edmonton. There are definitely bugs and rough edges (the bus names could definitely be better described/formatted, and there&amp;rsquo;s some serious geocoder issues), but I think the heavy lifting is out of the way. I guess now would be a good time to open up an invitations to anyone in Edmonton with an iPhone to become part of our free private beta. We&amp;rsquo;d love to hear what you think! Just send an email to &lt;a href="mailto:wrlach@gmail.com"&gt;wrlach@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>Oh, the lines! And some help for Edmonton.</title>
   <link>https://wrla.ch/blog/2010/04/oh-the-lines-and-some-help-for-edmonton/?utm_source=Transit-to-Go&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wrla-ch:-blog-2010-04-oh-the-lines-and-some-help-for-edmonton</guid>
   <pubDate>Sat, 10 Apr 2010 04:00:00 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/files/2010/04/linked_map1.jpg" alt="Map with new link nodes" title="Map with new link nodes" width="320" height="242" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-118" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A productive day on the transit development front. Finished up a few big features related to hbus.ca and Transit to Go:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Sped up the graph and database generation by an order of magnitude. Not too exciting from a user perspective, but I should now be able to iterate the codebase much faster.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Better transit stop / street graph linking: No more does libroutez simply try to find the closest street level vertice to link to when merging transit stops with street information: we now actually create _new_ street level vertices as needed and link to those. Upshot? Slightly better directions and prettier polylines. When I first thought up the algorithm a month ago, I thought I was totally brilliant, only to later find out that Andrew Byrd had done something almost identical a few months earlier for &lt;a href="http://github.com/andrewbyrd/graphserver"&gt;graphserver&lt;/a&gt;. Ah well, at least it&amp;rsquo;s implemented.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;I &lt;a href="http://gist.github.com/361848"&gt;coded up a script&lt;/a&gt; to automatically generate synthetic headsigns for GTFS feeds which don&amp;rsquo;t have them. This was needed to provide a sensible view for the Edmonton version of Transit to Go. All the props in the world for opening up your data guys, but can&amp;rsquo;t you do better than saying that all your buses go in the &amp;ldquo;1&amp;rdquo; direction? There&amp;rsquo;s a reason why it&amp;rsquo;s a required field you know. Not only would it help me, but &lt;a href="http://google.com/transit"&gt;Google Transit&lt;/a&gt; would give better results for your city as well.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>