<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<rss version="2.0">
 <channel>
  <title>William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Voltus'</title>
  <description>William Lachance's Log: Posts tagged 'Voltus'</description>
  <link>https://wrla.ch/tags/Voltus.html</link>
  <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2022 16:44:14 UT</lastBuildDate>
  <pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2022 16:44:14 UT</pubDate>
  <ttl>1800</ttl>
  <item>
   <title>90 days out and in</title>
   <link>https://wrla.ch/blog/2022/04/90-days-out-and-in/?utm_source=Voltus&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid isPermaLink="false">urn:https-wrla-ch:-blog-2022-04-90-days-out-and-in</guid>
   <pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2022 16:44:14 UT</pubDate>
   <author>William Lachance</author>
   <description>
&lt;p&gt;The 90 day mark just passed at my &lt;a href="https://voltus.co"&gt;new gig at Voltus&lt;/a&gt;, feels like a good time for a bit of self-reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, I think it&amp;rsquo;s been a good change and that it was the right time to leave Mozilla. Since I left, a few people have asked me why I chose to do so: while the full answer is pretty complicated (these things are never simple!), I think it does ultimately come down to wanting to try something new after 10+ years. I&amp;rsquo;ve accumulated a fair amount of expertise in web development and data engineering and I wanted to see if I could apply them to a new area that I cared about&amp;mdash; in this case, climate change and the energy transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voltus is a much younger and different company than Mozilla was, and there&amp;rsquo;s no shortage of things to learn and do. Energy markets are a rather interesting technical domain to work in&amp;mdash; a big intersection between politics, technology, and business. Lots of very old and very new things all at once. As a still-relatively young company, there is definitely more of a feeling that it&amp;rsquo;s possible to shape Voltus&amp;rsquo;s culture and practices, which has been interesting. There&amp;rsquo;s a bit of a balancing act between sharing what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned in previous roles while having the humility to recognize that there&amp;rsquo;s much you still don&amp;rsquo;t understand in a new workplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the downside, I have to admit that I do miss being able to work in the open. &lt;a href="https://www.canarymedia.com/articles/climatetech-finance/voltus-launches-1-3b-spac-to-help-businesses-reshape-their-power-use-and-ease-grid-stress"&gt;Voltus is currently in the process of going public&lt;/a&gt;, which has made me extra shy about saying much of anything about what I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on in a public forum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To some extent I&amp;rsquo;ve been scratching this itch by continuing to work on &lt;a href="https://irydium.dev"&gt;Irydium&lt;/a&gt; when I have the chance. I&amp;rsquo;ve done up a few new releases in the last couple of months, which I think have been fairly well received inside my very small community of people doing like-minded things. I&amp;rsquo;m planning on attending (at least part of) a &lt;a href="https://github.com/pyodide/pyodide/wiki/PyCon2022-sprint"&gt;pyodide sprint&lt;/a&gt; in early May, which I think should be a lot of fun as well as an opportunity to push browser-based data science forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve also kept more of a connection with Mozilla than I thought I would have: some video meetings with former colleagues, answering questions on Element (&lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Matrix"&gt;chat.mozilla.org&lt;/a&gt;), even &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/glean-dictionary/pulls?q=is%3Apr+author%3Awlach+is%3Aclosed"&gt;some pull requests&lt;/a&gt; where I felt like I could make a quick contribution. I&amp;rsquo;m still using Firefox, which has actually given me more perspective on some problems that people at Mozilla might not experience (e.g. &lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1536777"&gt;this screensharing bug&lt;/a&gt; which you&amp;rsquo;d only see if you&amp;rsquo;re using a WebRTC-based video conferencing solution like Google Meet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure to what extent this will continue: even if the source code to Firefox and the tooling that supports it is technically &amp;ldquo;open source&amp;rdquo;, outsiders like myself really have very limited visibility into what Mozilla is doing these days. This makes it difficult to really connect with much of what&amp;rsquo;s going on or know how I might be able to contribute. While it might be theoretically possible to join Mozilla&amp;rsquo;s Slack (at least last I checked), that feels like a rabbit hole I&amp;rsquo;d prefer not to go down. While I&amp;rsquo;m still interested in supporting Mozilla&amp;rsquo;s mission, I really don&amp;rsquo;t want more than one workplace chat tool in my life: there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of content there that is no longer relevant to me as a non-employee and (being honest) I&amp;rsquo;d rather leave behind. There&amp;rsquo;s lots more I could say about this, but probably best to leave it there: I understand that there&amp;rsquo;s reasons why things are the way they are, even if they make me a little sad.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>